♪ ♪ ♪
Hi, I'm Dessi Zaharieva and I'm here to talk to you
about managing activities of daily living and diabetes.
A little about me, I'm a Certified Exercise
Physiologist, a second degree black belt in TaeKwonDo,
a purple belt in Brazilian Jiujitsu, and I've
lived with type one diabetes for over 28 years.
In that time, I've learned a lot about
managing diabetes and staying active,
both for myself and for the patients I work with.
Today, I wanna talk about something we don't often discuss as part of
standardized diabetes education, activities of daily living, or ADLs.
When we think about staying active and managing blood glucose levels,
we usually picture structured workouts like
running, swimming, or going to the gym.
But ADLs are the everyday tasks we do
like cleaning, shopping, or yard work.
These might not seem much like activities per se, but they
can still have an impact on your blood glucose levels,
especially if they involve a lot of whole body movement.
♪ ♪ ♪
So what are ADLs?
ADLs are things you do every day or more
often to take care of yourself and your home.
They typically fall into two general categories.
Basic ADLs: these are things like showering,
brushing your teeth, or getting dressed.
They're usually not very intense, so they
may not affect blood glucose levels much.
And instrumental ADLs: are tasks like vacuuming,
gardening, walking around the store, or doing yard work.
These activities often use larger muscle groups
and can make your blood glucose levels drop,
especially if they take a long time.
♪ ♪ ♪
Some ADLs like cleaning or gardening work
your muscles and make your heart beat faster.
They're not as intense as a structured workout, but they
may still lower your blood glucose levels over time.
For example, ADLs get your muscles moving.
They make your heart beat faster.
They might cause large drops in glucose
levels, particularly if they last a long time.
ADLs can be a bit sneaky to manage because often you're
focused on the last minute holiday shopping you need
to do or running to meet your child spur of the moment.
Then all of a sudden you might be going low.
♪ ♪ ♪
Have you ever experienced what we call the mall low after hours of walking
around a mall or a big store like Costco, you feel the low blood sugars?
That's because walking for a long time can lower glucose
levels even if it doesn't feel like structured exercise.
A lot of the time when we go to pick up
groceries, it's not exactly a planned activity,
so it's easy to forget a quick snack or to
set an activity preset well before you go.
So how do you manage this?
♪ ♪ ♪
Let's talk about some tips for managing blood glucose levels during ADLs.
One, watch your blood glucose levels.
Check your continuous glucose monitoring or CGM system often.
For example, at least once every 20 to 30 minutes during the ADL.
Two, eat fast acting carbs.
Carry snacks like glucose tablets or candy and have
some If your blood glucose levels start to drop.
Consider eating fast acting carbs before and during the ADL
if you often experience drops in glucose with that activity.
Three, use activity presets.
Consider setting the Tidepool Loop walking preset,
or a custom preset with a lower amount of overall insulin if
you know you'll be doing an ADL for a long period of time.
♪ ♪ ♪
As we get older, we might spend more time on ADLs and
less time doing intense exercise, and that's okay.
It's still important to notice how these everyday
tasks could affect your blood glucose levels.
Try to notice any changes in the type and
intensity of activity you do as you get older.
♪ ♪ ♪
Now let's talk about the relationship between intensity and activity.
Tidepool Loop includes an RPE scale, which is a
rating of perceived exertion or intensity scale,
and this helps you track how an activity's intensity
feels and how it might affect your blood glucose levels.
For example, an exercise might feel hard the first time you do it,
but as you become more comfortable with that activity or you increase your
fitness levels, the intensity of that activity may be lower than before.
♪ ♪ ♪
Now I'm going to wrap up with a self-reflection exercise.
Over the next week, take 15 minutes to think about how ADLs
affect your blood glucose levels in different settings.
A few things you can ask yourself:
what chores or tasks do I do every day?
Do any of these activities make my blood glucose drop?
Are there patterns in when or how these tasks affect you?
How long does the activity last and how intense
is it when my blood glucose changes the most?
How does my career impact the work that I do?
If you work remotely or in person or both,
consider how this impacts your diabetes management.
Understanding how daily tasks impact your diabetes can help you
plan ahead and make it easier to handle these everyday challenges.
♪ ♪ ♪